in this exercise we're asked to
implement a factorial function with the
same functionality as a previous
exercise except instead of using a for
loop like we did before we're going to
use recursion
so a recursive function is one that
calls itself it contains a baseline
condition and that represents the stop
point at which the function returns
something and then it can use that
return value to climb back up all the
levels of the recursive calls it made
before reaching that condition
so the logic of calculating a factorial
actually lends itself really well for
this
let's define our function
we can call it factorial just like we
did before and then we're going to
provide
a single argument a positive integer and
we're told that we can be sure it will
always be a positive integer so we don't
have to worry too much about validation
which is nice
so we think about the way we implemented
this before recall how we decided to
decrement from the given number n down
to one because we always know a
factorial ends at one
we can use this to help us figure out
our baseline condition the factorial of
1 is always just 1 with no additional
operations and this allows us to say
something like if n
is equal to 1 then we just want to
return 1. factorial of 1 is always 1.
so
this way whenever the function is called
with an argument of 1 it will return 1
without having to recursively call
itself which is what we're going to do
down here on line 6.
so now we have our stop condition in
place we can think about how we can
work the recursive function call into
our logic
and what we want to do here is get the
result of multiplying n by
the factorial of n minus 1 right
and we want to
return that
because if we think about it if we look
at what a factorial is factorial 5
is
times 4 times 3 times 2 times 1 right
well
what is factorial 4
factorial 4 is 4 times 3 times 2 times
1. so really factorial 5 is just 5 times
factorial 4.
similarly factorial 4 is just factorial
4 times
[Music]
factorial 3.
factorial 3 is really just fact 3 times
factorial 2
and factorial 2 is really just 2 times
factorial 1 which we know is 1.
so the nice thing is when we call this
let's keep with our example 5 here if we
call an outer function call 2 factorial
5 this is how it gets evaluated
n will be assigned to 5. we'll evaluate
the condition and 5 is not equal to 1 so
we jump down here to line 6 and then
this becomes 5 times factorial 4.
now javascript has to evaluate this so
it again calls the factorial function
with 4 as an argument so we call it
again n is assigned to 4 and it's not
equal to 1. so now we need to look at
down here we're getting 4 times
factorial 3. factorial 3 needs to be
evaluated so we're going to assign n to
3 and then n is not equal to 1 so we
come down here and evaluate 3 times
factorial 2.
in order to evaluate this factorial 2
needs to be evaluated so we assign n to
2 and 2 is not equal to 1 so we're going
to evaluate this which becomes 2 times
factorial 1. and then at this point when
we call factorial 1 n is assigned to 1
at this point n will be equal to 1 so
this returns true and we return the
value 1. so when we try to evaluate this
expression here in the recursive stack
this is going to evaluate to 1.
and this is nice because now this is
just a simple multiplication operation
javascript can evaluate that no problem
without any kind of recursion at all so
this of course is going to return 2
and then this becomes because of this
return keyword here the return value for
this invocation of factorial so this
becomes 3 times 2
which returns 6.
and then this 6 becomes the return value
of this factorial function call
factorial 3
so this becomes 4 times 6
which resolves to 24
and then this 24 becomes the return
value of factorial 4.
so this becomes 5 times 24 which
turns out to 120 and then finally this
120 becomes the return value of our
original outer call to factorial when we
passed an argument of 5.
so that's kind of how the function is
working
and if i go ahead and paste in
my test cases here
we'll be able to see it in action i'm
going to head to the terminal
and i'm going to
run the
file and as you can see we are getting
our correct value for
factorial
so that's how we can use recursion to
help us solve these kind of repetitive
problems that have a stop condition